Every time you make a swap on a DEX, there's a good chance
a bot saw your transaction in the mempool before it was included in
a block, calculated that it could profit from your trade, inserted its own
transaction before yours to move the price, let your trade execute at the
worse price, then sold immediately after. You paid more than you had to,
and the bot pocketed the difference. This is MEV — Maximal Extractable Value
— and it extracts over $1 billion from users every year.
Welcome to QuantiFire. MEV is money that validators or block
producers can extract by reordering, inserting, or censoring transactions within
a block. Originally called Miner Extractable Value in proof-of-work, it's
now called Maximal Extractable Value. Understanding MEV tells you why
your swaps get worse execution than you expect, and what
you can do about it.
The mempool: Ethereum transactions don't go directly into blocks. They
sit in the public mempool — a shared waiting room
visible to everyone. Every transaction you submit shows the world
what tokens you're swapping, what slippage you'll tolerate, your exact
transaction parameters. MEV bots scan this in real time.
Types of MEV: sandwich attacks are the most user-harmful — pure
extraction from retail users. Arbitrage MEV is mostly beneficial — it
restores price efficiency across DEXes. Liquidation MEV maintains protocol solvency. JIT
— just-in-time liquidity — is mixed: users get slightly better prices,
existing LPs get slightly less fees. MEV-Boost, used by 90% of
Ethereum validators, redirects most MEV value to validators — democratizing MEV
revenue. Defence: use private RPC endpoints like Flashbots Protect or MEV
Blocker, and keep slippage tolerance tight.
Next: Sandwich Attacks specifically — the exact mechanics,
how much it costs you on each trade,
and how to calculate your exposure. Subscribe. QuantiFire.