May 2022. LUNA collapses from $80 to $0 in 72
hours. Billions in positions across Anchor, Venus, and Aave are
instantly undercollateralized. Liquidation bots race to clear positions, dumping collateral
onto thin markets. Each liquidation drives prices lower. Lower prices
trigger more liquidations. The cascade propagates across the entire DeFi
ecosystem. By the end: $300 billion in market cap evaporated.
This is the liquidation cascade — and it's a structural
feature of overcollateralized lending.
Welcome to QuantiFire. Liquidation cascades are one of the most
dangerous systemic risks in DeFi. They arise from the feedback
loop between falling prices, forced selling, and further price declines.
Understanding the mechanics helps you position your own portfolios defensively
and identify systemic risk building up in the market.
The cascade mechanism: step one — asset price drops below a
critical level, multiple positions reach a health factor below 1. Step
two — liquidation bots execute, selling collateral on DEXes at market
price. Step three — that selling pressure drives prices further down.
Step four — new positions breach the health factor threshold, triggering
more liquidations. Repeat until price finds natural support or collateral pools
are exhausted. The feedback amplifies because all liquidations sell the same
collateral asset — ETH — and price impact is additive across
hundreds of simultaneous events.
This liquidation density map shows how much ETH collateral becomes liquidatable
at each price level. The red bars — prices below $2,000
— represent hundreds of millions in positions that would cascade. When
ETH was at $2,000, a drop to $1,600 would unlock $300
million in forced selling. That selling pushes price to $1,400, unlocking
another $420 million. The March 2020 Black Thursday event followed exactly
this pattern — ETH dropped 43% in 24 hours and MakerDAO
liquidation auctions had zero bidders. The protocol ended with $4 million
in bad debt sold for zero DAI.
In a cascade, every second counts. Automated position management tools —
DeFiSaver automation, Instadapp — can add collateral or reduce debt automatically
when your health factor drops below your threshold. They move faster
than any manual response. Set these up before you need them.
Never rely on being able to manually respond during a cascade
— gas prices will spike 100 times and the UI will
be down. Final episode of Series 3: Regulatory Risk — SEC,
FATF, MiCA, and what the evolving global regulatory framework means for
your DeFi positions. Subscribe. QuantiFire.