Every major bank, hedge fund, and now DeFi protocol needs to answer one
question: how much could we lose in a really bad day? Value at
Risk — VaR — is the industry's standard answer. It's a single number
that regulators require, risk managers report, and traders live by. Today I'll show
you three ways to calculate it and when each one lies to you.
Welcome to QuantiFire. VaR was popularized by JP Morgan's RiskMetrics in the
1990s and became the global risk standard post-Basel II. It's defined simply:
the maximum loss not exceeded with probability alpha over a given horizon.
At 95% confidence over one day — 5% VaR — you're saying:
on 95 out of 100 trading days, losses won't exceed this number.
Method one: Historical Simulation. Take your portfolio's actual historical P and
L series — say 500 days. Sort losses from worst to
best. The 5% VaR is the loss at the 25th worst
observation — that's 500 times 0.05. No distributional assumptions at all.
The formula reads: VaR at confidence alpha equals the negative
of the empirical alpha-quantile of historical returns. Pros: fully non-parametric,
captures fat tails and actual market behavior. Cons: completely dependent
on the historical window. If your window doesn't include a
crisis, your VaR will chronically underestimate risk.
Method two: Parametric Normal. Assume returns are normally distributed. VaR
equals the negative of the mean minus z-alpha times sigma
— where z equals 1.645 for 95% confidence. Scale to
portfolio value by multiplying by total capital. Pros: fast, analytically
tractable, easy to decompose by asset.
Cons: financial returns have fat tails. The normal distribution massively underestimates
tail losses. A 5-sigma event that should happen once every 3.5
million days happens every few years in real markets.
Method three: Parametric Student-t. Replace the normal with a t-distribution with
estimated degrees of freedom nu. For nu around 4 to 6,
you get realistic fat tails that match equity return data. As
nu approaches infinity, you recover the normal. The gold t-distribution curve
is heavier in the tails — that means higher VaR estimates
that better reflect true market risk. This is strictly better than
the normal method for any financial return series.
VaR Scaling: the square-root-of-time rule. To convert a 1-day VaR to
a T-day VaR, multiply by the square root of T. A
5-day VaR is roughly 2.2 times the 1-day VaR. A 22-day
monthly VaR is about 4.7 times the daily figure.
Important caveat: this holds only if returns are
independent and identically distributed. In practice, volatility clusters
— bad days follow bad days. The square-root
rule understates multi-day VaR during market stress periods.
VaR's biggest limitation: it tells you the threshold, but says nothing
about how bad losses can get beyond that threshold. Strategy A
and Strategy B can have identical VaR numbers. Strategy A loses
exactly the VaR amount when things go wrong. Strategy B occasionally
loses ten times the VaR — there's a hidden tail spike
the VaR number completely ignores. These are wildly different risk profiles.
This is why Expected Shortfall — also called CVaR or Conditional VaR —
was developed. CVaR equals the expected loss given that you have already breached
VaR. It captures the full shape of the tail — the red zone.
While VaR draws a line in the sand, CVaR asks: if we cross
that line, how bad does it get on average? Basel Three and most
modern risk frameworks now require CVaR to be reported alongside VaR.
For DeFi: on-chain VaR needs two extra risk terms that
no price series captures. First — liquidation cascade risk: during
market stress, protocols become highly correlated and forced liquidations amplify
losses systemically. Second — smart contract exploit risk: rare, but
when it happens it can be catastrophic and instantaneous. A
standard VaR model that ignores these will chronically underestimate the
true risk of a DeFi portfolio.
Key takeaways. One: always report VaR alongside CVaR — VaR alone says
nothing about how severe losses can get once you've breached the threshold.
Two: know your historical window and challenge it — if it doesn't
include a crisis period, your VaR is optimistic. Three: if your return
series has excess kurtosis above 3 — which is most financial assets
— use Student-t, not Normal. Four: for DeFi, add liquidation cascade and
smart contract exploit risk on top of any price-return VaR.
Next episode: Factor Models — how quants decompose every
return into systematic exposures, and why that changes everything
about how you think about alpha. Subscribe. QuantiFire.