A DAO is supposed to be the purest form of democracy: token
holders vote on protocol decisions. But what if someone could borrow $1
billion in tokens for 12 seconds, vote on a governance proposal that
empties the treasury, and repay the tokens — all in one transaction?
This isn't hypothetical. It happened to Beanstalk Farms in April 2022. $182
million stolen through a governance flash loan attack.
Welcome to QuantiFire. Governance is the mechanism by which
DeFi protocols upgrade themselves, manage treasuries, and adjust parameters.
It's also one of the largest attack surfaces in
DeFi. Today I'll cover the major governance attack vectors:
flash loan voting, token concentration, and malicious proposal execution.
The Beanstalk attack: flash loan over $1 billion in stablecoins, deposit
into Beanstalk to receive governance tokens, immediately vote on two pre-staged
malicious proposals — one to donate all Beanstalk assets to the
attacker's wallet. Since the attacker held majority of tokens, both proposals
passed instantly. Protocol sent all assets to the attacker's wallet. The
attacker repaid flash loans and kept $182 million. The fatal flaw:
no time delay between vote and execution.
The fix: timelock plus snapshot separation. Standard safe governance model
— Compound Governor Bravo: proposal submitted, then 2-day voting delay
— this prevents flash loan attacks since votes use the
balance at the proposal block. Then a 3-day voting period.
After passing, a 2-day timelock before execution. Total: 7 days
minimum from proposal to execution. Flash loans are same-block —
irrelevant to the snapshot. The 7-day delay also gives the
community time to react to malicious proposals before they execute.
Next: Liquidation Cascades — when DeFi dominoes fall. How
one large liquidation triggers others in a chain reaction
that can destabilize entire protocols. Subscribe. QuantiFire.