You've found a strategy that returns 18% per year. Is
that alpha — genuine skill generating returns above what the
market compensates — or is it just levered exposure to
known risk factors that any investor could replicate cheaply?
Factor models answer this question. And
the answer is almost always humbling.
Welcome to QuantiFire. Factor models are the
fundamental decomposition tool of quantitative finance.
Every return stream can be broken into systematic components
— factors — plus an idiosyncratic residual. Understanding that
decomposition tells you what you're actually being paid for
and whether that compensation is efficient.
Every asset return decomposes into three parts:
alpha, factor exposure, and idiosyncratic noise.
Alpha — shown in gold — is the return you
generated through genuine skill, unexplained by any systematic factor.
Factor exposure — in teal — is your
sensitivity to market-wide forces like momentum, value, or
size, multiplied by how those factors performed.
Idiosyncratic noise — in red — is just randomness that no factor
explains. The key insight: if most of your return comes from factor
exposure, you are not generating alpha. You are harvesting known risk premiums
— and you should be paying much lower fees.
The original model was CAPM — a single factor: the
market. Everything in excess of the market return adjusted for
beta is alpha. Sharpe (1964) and Lintner (1965) showed that
if markets are efficient, beta fully explains cross-sectional return differences.
But empirically, the single-factor model fails. Stocks
with certain characteristics earn consistent returns that
pure market exposure doesn't explain.
Small-cap stocks systematically outperform large-cap. Value stocks outperform growth.
Past winners keep winning. These are returns that beta
alone simply cannot explain — which means CAPM's alpha
is contaminated by these hidden factor exposures.
Fama and French published their 3-Factor Model in 1993 in the
Journal of Financial Economics. It adds two factors to the market.
MKT is the original market factor. SMB — Small Minus Big —
captures the size premium: small-cap stocks earn more than large-cap on average.
HML — High Minus Low — captures the value
premium: value stocks with high book-to-market ratios earn more
than growth stocks. Together these two factors explain about
90% of the cross-sectional variation in stock returns.
The single market factor of CAPM was published in 1964.
Fama and French extended it to three factors
in 1993, adding the size and value premiums.
Carhart added a fourth factor in 1997: MOM — momentum
— trailing 12-month return minus the last month. Momentum is
one of the most robust and controversial anomalies in finance.
Fama and French extended to five factors in 2015,
adding RMW — Robust Minus Weak profitability — and
CMA — Conservative Minus Aggressive investment. Together these five
factors explain most of the variation in equity returns.
The Fama-French 5-Factor model is now the standard
baseline for factor attribution in equity research.
Portfolio attribution: decompose your returns into factor exposures. This portfolio
returned 18% — let's see where it actually came from.
If 80% of your alpha is just HML loading — value factor
exposure — you are not an alpha generator. You are a value
investor with leverage. You could replicate that exposure at a fraction of
the cost with a value ETF. This insight, from Tulchinsky et al.'s
Finding Alphas, is what drives the factor ETF industry.
Two portfolios can have identical total volatility
but completely different factor exposure profiles.
Portfolio A has 80% of its risk concentrated in market
beta. Portfolio B diversifies across multiple factors. Both show 15%
volatility — but Portfolio B is genuinely better diversified. Factor
models make this visible. Without them, you're flying blind.
Factor construction in DeFi: on-chain data generates novel factor
signals that map directly onto the Fama-French framework.
TVL Momentum — protocols gaining total value locked outperform — is the
DeFi analogue of the size premium. Revenue Yield — protocol fees divided
by fully diluted value — maps to the value premium.
Holder concentration — a novel on-chain factor with no traditional
analogue — captures distributed ownership as a quality signal. We'll
build these factors from on-chain data in a future episode.
The covariance matrix estimated via factor models is
far more stable than direct sample estimation.
Direct estimation of a 500-asset covariance matrix requires
over 125,000 parameters — highly unstable unless you
have thousands of years of data.
With a 5-factor model, you estimate only 5 loadings per
asset — just 2,500 parameters total. Same 500 assets. Far
more stable. This is the core advantage of factor-based risk
models used by Barra, Axioma, and every major quantitative shop.
Run a factor regression on any strategy before declaring
alpha. Use the Fama-French 5 factors as your baseline.
If your alpha shrinks to near-zero after factor adjustment, your strategy
is factor harvesting — valuable, but very different from true alpha.
Only what survives factor adjustment is worth calling edge.
Next: the Black-Litterman Model — how to inject your own market
views into a portfolio optimizer in a mathematically rigorous way. This
is how the big funds do it. Subscribe. QuantiFire.