The Sharpe Ratio is the single most cited performance metric
in finance. It's on every fund factsheet, every backtest report,
every quant resume. And it has a fundamental flaw that
can make a catastrophically risky strategy look like a safe,
consistent winner. Today I'll show you exactly what that flaw
is, and the fix that professionals use instead.
Welcome to QuantiFire. Both the Sharpe and Sortino ratios measure risk-adjusted
return — how much return are you generating per unit of
risk taken. But they disagree on what counts as risk. That
disagreement matters enormously when your return distribution is asymmetric — which
in DeFi and systematic trading, it almost always is.
The Sharpe Ratio: your average excess return above the risk-free
rate, divided by the standard deviation of all your returns.
The numerator — shown in teal — is
your excess return above the risk-free rate.
The denominator — shown in red — is the standard deviation of
ALL returns, up AND down. A month where you made eight percent?
That goes in. A month where you lost four percent? That also
goes in. The Sharpe treats both identically as volatility to be penalized.
Here is the flaw made concrete. Strategy A returns a flat
two percent every single month — no drama, no variation.
Strategy B averages the same two percent but with volatile swings:
some months of plus eight percent, some of minus four.
Both strategies have nearly identical Sharpe Ratios. But a rational investor
prefers Strategy B — those plus eight percent months are gains,
not risk. The Sharpe Ratio cannot tell the difference.
The Sortino Ratio fixes this. The denominator uses only downside
deviation — the standard deviation of returns that fall below
a target threshold, usually zero or the risk-free rate.
Returns above the threshold — shown in teal — are completely ignored
in the denominator. Returns below it — shown in red — are
the only ones penalized. You are penalized only for bad volatility.
Concretely: a strategy with fifteen percent upside deviation and five percent
downside deviation. Sharpe uses a combined sigma of about eleven percent.
Sortino uses only five. Same strategy — radically different scores —
and the Sortino tells the more honest story.
Use the Sharpe Ratio when return distributions are approximately
symmetric and normal — classical equity long-only, diversified factor
portfolios where upside and downside volatility are roughly equal.
Use the Sortino when strategies have skewed distributions — options
writing, trend following, yield farming — any strategy where you
care about the asymmetry between wins and losses.
And use the Calmar Ratio when you care specifically
about maximum drawdown — the preferred metric for CTA
traders who manage to explicit drawdown thresholds.
Now the most important warning. Some strategies manufacture high Sharpe
Ratios by selling tail risk — consistently collecting small premiums
from selling naked puts or short volatility strategies.
This produces a smooth return series right up until
a volatility spike wipes them out. Watch this equity
curve: beautiful, steady growth, Sharpe of two point one.
Then a sudden cliff. The Sharpe looked great the
whole time. This is the Sharpe Ratio trap.
Always pair Sharpe with tail metrics: maximum drawdown,
CVaR at ninety-five percent, skewness, and kurtosis.
For DeFi specifically: liquidity provision strategies have asymmetric profiles
— gradual impermanent loss accumulation punctuated by fee income
creates a right-skewed return distribution. Use Sortino here.
Funding rate arbitrage has near-normally distributed daily returns with rare
positive funding spike events. Sharpe works there, but always pair
it with CVaR to catch the spike risk.
Never evaluate a strategy with a single metric. If the Sortino
is significantly higher than the Sharpe, the strategy has positive skew
— a fat right tail — that's usually good news.
If they are roughly equal, the distribution
is near-symmetric and the metrics agree.
If the Sortino is lower than the Sharpe, the strategy has negative skew
— hidden tail risk lurking below the surface. That is your red flag.
Minimum reporting standard: Sharpe, Sortino, Max Drawdown,
and Skewness. Never just one number.
Next up: Value at Risk — how do quants put
an actual dollar figure on the worst-case loss? It's the
number regulators require, and it has some nasty surprises. Subscribe
and I'll see you in the next episode. QuantiFire.