In 1956, a Bell Labs scientist named John Kelly published a
formula that — if applied correctly — provably maximises your long-term
wealth growth rate faster than any other betting strategy.
It's used by everyone from professional blackjack card counters
to quantitative hedge funds. And it comes with a
trap that destroys accounts if you're not careful.
The Kelly Criterion answers one question: given a bet with known
probabilities and payoffs, what fraction of your bankroll should you risk?
The answer is counterintuitive — not as much as
you think, and definitely not all of it. Today
I'll give you the single-bet formula, the multi-asset extension,
and the fractional Kelly approach used in real trading.
The Kelly formula: f-star equals p minus q over b.
p is the probability of winning. q equals one minus p — the probability
of losing. b is the net odds: how much you win per unit risked.
f-star is the optimal fraction of your bankroll to
bet each time. This single formula encodes the entire
trade-off between edge, odds, and position sizing.
Concrete example: a fair coin where heads pays 2 to
1. p equals 0.5, q equals 0.5, b equals 2.
Kelly says bet 25% of your bankroll each flip.
Not 50% — that feels right but a losing streak compounds ruinously.
Not 100% — one loss wipes you out. 25%, because the mathematics
proves that is the exact fraction that maximises compound wealth over time.
Kelly maximises the geometric mean — the expected value of the
logarithm of wealth. G of f equals p times log of
one plus f-b, plus q times log of one minus f.
Maximise G over f. The solution is f-star at 25%.
Notice: G rises to a peak at Kelly, then falls
steeply. Betting more than f-star produces lower geometric growth.
Paradoxically, overbetting makes you grow slower and eventually go
to zero. This is the Kelly trap: a winning
strategy played at twice Kelly will eventually ruin you.
At 10% — well below Kelly — the bankroll grows slowly but safely.
At full Kelly — 25% — the bankroll
compounds at the maximum long-run growth rate.
At 50% — twice Kelly — growth is actually slower
than full Kelly. The extra risk is not compensated.
At 75% — reckless overbetting — the bankroll collapses toward
zero. A strategy with a 50% win rate, played at
75%, will eventually ruin you. This is the Kelly trap.
For a portfolio of N assets, the multi-asset Kelly maximises
the expected log return over all weight vectors w.
In the Gaussian approximation, the optimal Kelly portfolio is
proportional to the inverse covariance matrix times expected returns
— identical to the Markowitz tangency portfolio. Kelly and
Markowitz converge in the Gaussian world.
Where they diverge is in fat-tailed distributions, where
Kelly is more conservative because log utility penalises
extreme losses far more severely than mean-variance does.
Full Kelly is extremely aggressive and highly sensitive to estimation
errors in p and b. A 10% overestimate of edge
can drive you to bet twice the optimal amount.
In practice, traders use fractional Kelly. Half Kelly gives you
about 75% of the long-run growth rate of full Kelly
with dramatically lower drawdowns and variance of outcomes.
Half-Kelly is the professional compromise between growth maximisation and
risk control. Never use more than full Kelly.
Applied to yield strategy selection: the Kelly fraction for
each protocol allocation is proportional to expected yield minus
the risk-free rate, divided by the variance of that
yield. Higher-yielding, lower-variance protocols receive larger allocations.
Smart contract exploit risk dramatically reduces the Kelly fraction.
A negative 100% event has a log utility of
negative infinity — total ruin. The Kelly fraction collapses
to near-zero for any protocol with uncapped exploit risk.
This is why you must explicitly price smart contract
risk before applying Kelly to any DeFi yield allocation.
Kelly is the long-run optimal sizing formula — but only
when your probability estimates are accurate. Use half-Kelly in practice.
Never use more than full Kelly — overbetting causes ruin even with positive
edge. Always add a hard stop: Kelly is a ceiling, not a mandate.
For DeFi: price smart contract exploit risk before applying
Kelly. The formula is a ceiling, not a mandate.
Next: Risk Parity — the portfolio construction method that ignores
expected returns entirely and allocates purely based on risk contribution.
Used by Bridgewater's All Weather fund. Subscribe. QuantiFire.