The narrative that crypto is purely speculative — with no fundamental
value anchor — is wrong. Every DeFi protocol generates revenue. Every
one has costs. Many have discounted cash flows you can model.
The same valuation frameworks that work for stocks work for DeFi
protocols if you know how to translate the metrics. Today I'll
show you the DeFi-native equivalents of P/E, P/B, and DCF.
Welcome to QuantiFire. Quantitative value investing — buying assets below fundamental
value and waiting for reversion — is one of the oldest
and most empirically robust investment strategies. The HML factor in Fama-French
is essentially systematic value. The question is: what is fundamental value
for a DeFi protocol? Let's build the framework.
Every DeFi protocol has revenue from trading fees, lending spread, and
liquidation fees. It has costs from token emissions and security. The
TradFi-to-DeFi metric translation: Price-to-Earnings maps to fully diluted valuation over annualized
revenue — that's your P/S ratio. Price-to-Book maps to FDV over
TVL — total value locked is the DeFi equivalent of book
value. Earnings yield maps to revenue over FDV. And growth maps
to TVL and revenue growth rates. Key data sources: Token Terminal
for revenue and P/S ratios, DeFiLlama for TVL, Dune Analytics for
custom on-chain queries.
This scatter plot maps DeFi protocols by FDV over TVL on
the horizontal axis against annualized revenue yield on the vertical axis.
The value zone — FDV/TVL below 0.8 and revenue yield above
30% — contains Uniswap, Curve, and Aave. These are the protocols
generating substantial real revenue relative to their managed assets at reasonable
valuations. Protocol X at top-right — high FDV/TVL, low revenue yield
— represents a speculative premium with no fundamental support. The screening
criteria: P/S below 10, revenue yield above 10%, and positive revenue
growth. Combine with momentum from episode 25 to get value at
improving momentum — the strongest systematic signal combination in any asset
class.
DeFi protocols have real fundamentals: revenue, growth, token cash flow. Build
a screening model using P/S below 10 plus revenue yield above
10% plus positive revenue growth as the value filter. Combine with
momentum to get value at improving momentum — the strongest systematic
signal combination in any asset class. Final episode of Series 4:
On-Chain Alpha Signals — the DeFi data revolution. Wallet tracking, TVL
flows, liquidity migration signals, and how to build a systematic on-chain
data edge. Subscribe. QuantiFire.