Mean-Variance Optimization tells you to build a single portfolio on
the efficient frontier. But real investors — from retail traders
to billionaires — don't behave this way. They mentally separate
their money into accounts: a safety layer, a growth layer,
a speculation layer. Behavioral Portfolio Theory formalizes this behavior and
produces portfolio structures that look radically different from Markowitz —
and in many ways, more rational given actual human psychology.
Welcome to QuantiFire. Behavioral Portfolio Theory was developed by
Shefrin and Statman in 2000. It extends Prospect Theory
into a portfolio framework. Understanding it has two applications:
avoiding its pitfalls in your own decision-making, and understanding
why retail and institutional investors hold the positions they
do — which generates the anomalies quants exploit.
The mental accounting framework: people don't think of their entire
wealth as one unified portfolio. They think in mental accounts
— buckets with different purposes, risk tolerances, and time horizons.
The safety layer: money you cannot afford to lose —
70 to 80% of capital. Risk tolerance near zero. Instruments:
cash, FDIC insured deposits, stablecoin yield on Aave. The income
layer: steady return for reinvestment — 15 to 20% of
capital. Instruments: stETH staking, liquid staking tokens, bonds. The growth
layer: long-term wealth accumulation — 5 to 10% of capital.
Instruments: ETH, BTC, blue-chip DeFi tokens. The speculation layer: get-rich
potential, accept total loss — 1 to 5% of capital.
Instruments: options, altcoins, high-APY DeFi farms, new protocol tokens.
The behavioral portfolio framework maps naturally to DeFi allocation. Safety:
USDC or USDT in Aave or Compound — 4 to
5% APY, minimal smart contract risk. Income: stETH staking, rETH,
liquid staking — 4 to 5% plus ETH price exposure.
Growth: ETH, BTC, blue-chip DeFi governance tokens like UNI and
AAVE — market-linked returns. Speculation: high-APY farms, new protocol tokens,
structured DeFi products — accept full loss. This framework is
psychologically comfortable AND financially reasonable if the layers are sized
correctly. The key rule: size the speculation layer to what
you can afford to lose entirely. A speculative loss should
not psychologically contaminate your growth and safety layers.
If you use mental accounting — and you do, everyone does
— use it deliberately. Define your layers explicitly, size them based
on objective financial needs, and set rules for each layer separately.
Acknowledge that your speculative layer will likely return negative 100% —
size it accordingly. The structure prevents a speculative loss from psychologically
contaminating your growth and safety layers. Final episode of the season:
Black Swan Events — Nassim Taleb's framework for tail risk, what
makes an event a Black Swan, and how to position your
portfolio for events that models say can't happen but keep happening
anyway. Subscribe. QuantiFire.