The DAO hack: $60 million. Poly Network: $611 million. Ronin Bridge:
$625 million. Wormhole: $320 million. Total DeFi hacks since 2019: over
$5 billion stolen. Not from exchanges being hacked in the traditional
sense — from bugs in smart contract code that anyone could
exploit. Today I'm breaking down the five most common attack vectors,
the code-level vulnerability, and how each one is prevented.
Welcome to QuantiFire. Smart contracts are immutable programs running on
public blockchains. Their code is open source — any attacker
can study it. Any bug is a potential exploit. Understanding
these vulnerabilities is essential whether you're building protocols, auditing code,
or deciding which protocols to trust with your capital.
The five most damaging attack categories. Number one: reentrancy — the
original DeFi hack that drained The DAO of $60 million in
2016. Number two: access control failure — a single missing check
enabled the $611 million Poly Network hack. Number three: oracle manipulation
— flash loans used to distort prices across multiple attacks totaling
$500 million or more. Number four: logic and economic design flaws
— Mango Markets lost $116 million to a price manipulation strategy
that wasn't technically a code bug. Number five: integer overflow —
affects older contracts written before Solidity 0.8.
The reentrancy pattern: the attacker calls withdraw on the victim contract.
The victim sends ETH to the attacker's contract. The attacker's receive
function calls withdraw again — before the first call completes. The
victim hasn't updated its balance yet, so it sends ETH again.
Repeat until the pool is drained. The fix: Checks-Effects-Interactions pattern. Update
all state — set balance to zero — before any external
call. Or use a nonReentrant mutex lock. Modern best practice: both.
Before trusting a protocol with capital: has it been audited by
at least two top-tier firms? Is there a bug bounty program?
Is the code open source and time-tested? What's the largest withdrawal
that can happen without a time-lock? These four questions are your
minimum security due diligence. Next: Governance Attacks — when DAOs turn
against their users. Flash loan voting, token concentration risks, and the
malicious proposal that drained a $100 million treasury. Subscribe. QuantiFire.