$5 billion stolen from DeFi protocols — almost all of it
from preventable bugs. The same attack patterns repeat across hundreds of
hacks: reentrancy, missing access control, unchecked external calls, price oracle manipulation.
In this episode, I'll show you the defensive code patterns that
prevent each category of attack. If you're building on-chain or evaluating
protocol security — this is your checklist.
Welcome to QuantiFire. We covered the attack vectors in
episode 21. Today is the builder's perspective: the design
patterns, code conventions, and architectural decisions that make contracts
resistant to each attack class. These patterns are distilled
from OpenZeppelin, Trail of Bits, ConsenSys Diligence, and the
post-mortems of every major DeFi hack.
Pattern one: Checks-Effects-Interactions — the most important pattern in Solidity.
For every state-changing function: first, validate all inputs and preconditions
with require statements. Second, update all state variables. Third, call
external contracts last. The vulnerable pattern on the left sends
ETH before updating the balance — an attacker's receive function
can call withdraw again before the balance is updated, draining
the pool. The correct pattern on the right updates the
balance first, then interacts. The reentrancy attack is impossible because
the state is already updated when the external call happens.
Add OpenZeppelin's nonReentrant modifier as belt-and-suspenders protection.
The six non-negotiable security patterns. One: CEI pattern on every
state-changing function. Two: ReentrancyGuard with the nonReentrant modifier from OpenZeppelin.
Three: role-based access control — every sensitive function must restrict
callers explicitly. Never leave admin functions callable by arbitrary addresses.
Four: Chainlink price feed for oracles — never use AMM
spot price as a primary oracle for collateral valuation. It
is manipulatable with flash loans. Five: 48-hour timelock on all
admin operations — this is what prevents governance flash loan
attacks. Six: Solidity 0.8 or higher for automatic integer overflow
protection. The cost of an audit is 30 to 100
thousand dollars. The cost of a hack is everything. Always
audit with at least one professional firm before mainnet.
Security is architecture, not an afterthought. Build with Checks-Effects-Interactions, ReentrancyGuard,
and AccessControl from the start. Use Chainlink for oracles. Add
timelocks on all admin operations. Then audit with at least
one professional firm before mainnet. Final episode of Series 5:
Blockchain Consensus — Proof of Work vs Proof of Stake,
why the Merge happened, and what the security implications are
for the assets you hold. Subscribe. QuantiFire.