A smart contract is completely isolated from the outside world. It
can't see what ETH costs on Coinbase. It can't access interest
rates, stock prices, or weather data. Without external data, lending protocols
can't calculate collateral values, options protocols can't settle, prediction markets can't
resolve. The oracle problem is DeFi's most critical infrastructure challenge —
and Chainlink is the dominant solution.
Welcome to QuantiFire. Chainlink is a decentralized oracle network that aggregates
data from multiple sources and delivers it on-chain with cryptographic security
guarantees. It powers over $75 billion in DeFi TVL across hundreds
of protocols. Understanding how it works — and where it can
fail — is essential for any DeFi participant or builder.
Chainlink's architecture: multiple off-chain premium data providers each provide
price data independently. A network of independent node operators
— typically 7 to 31 per feed — each
independently query the data sources, aggregate them, and sign
the result. An on-chain aggregator collects responses from all
nodes, removes outliers, and reports the median on-chain. To
corrupt a Chainlink feed, an attacker must corrupt a
majority of node operators simultaneously — prohibitively expensive.
The price is updated on-chain when price moves more than 0.5% from
the last on-chain value — the deviation trigger — or when a
heartbeat interval of typically 1 hour has passed. Current best practice: use
Chainlink as the primary feed with a Uniswap TWAP as a circuit
breaker. If Chainlink deviates from TWAP by more than 5%, halt the
protocol and require manual intervention. Every DeFi protocol you interact with depends
on oracle accuracy. Before using any protocol, check what oracle it uses
and how many nodes back the feed.
Final episode of Series 2: dYdX Perpetuals — how perpetual futures
work, what funding rates are, and how the funding rate arbitrage
trade generates yield in all market conditions. Subscribe. QuantiFire.