If you've ever run a mean-variance optimizer and gotten portfolio
weights like 120% in one asset and negative 80% in
another, you've experienced the input sensitivity problem of classical MVO.
In 1990, Goldman Sachs researchers Fischer Black and
Robert Litterman published the fix. It changed how
institutional portfolio managers build portfolios forever.
Black-Litterman combines a Bayesian prior — the
market equilibrium — with your active views.
Using matrix algebra, it produces stable, intuitive portfolio weights.
The genius is in the starting point: instead of
guessing expected returns — which causes all the instability
— you reverse-engineer what the market is already implying.
Start with market-cap weights. The market equilibrium implies these weights
are optimal for some aggregate level of risk aversion delta.
Reverse-engineer the implied expected returns: pi equals delta times
the covariance matrix times the market-cap weights. Pi is
your prior — the market's best guess of expected
returns, reflected in current prices. It's the neutral starting
point before you add any views of your own.
Suppose you have K views. Each view is expressed
as P times mu equals q plus epsilon-views.
P is a K by N pick matrix describing which assets your view
is about. Q is the vector of view returns. Omega captures your uncertainty
in each view — the smaller omega, the more confident you are.
Concrete example: you believe US Tech will outperform EU Banks
by 3% annually. P has plus-one for US Tech and
minus-one for EU Banks. Q equals 0.03. Omega-one-one is your
uncertainty squared — your confidence in this specific forecast.
Combine the prior and views using Bayes' theorem. The
Black-Litterman posterior mean is this formula — a precision-weighted
average of the prior and your views.
Tau is a scalar expressing how uncertain you are
about the prior. Typically set between 0.025 and 0.05.
High confidence views — small omega — pull the
posterior strongly toward your forecast. Low confidence views barely
move it from equilibrium. This is exactly the Bayesian
behaviour you want from a portfolio model.
Plug the BL posterior into the standard mean-variance optimizer.
Here in blue are the market-cap weights — the
neutral starting point when you have no views.
In teal are the BL weights after expressing the view that
US equities will outperform. The optimizer tilts toward US equities and
away from EU — in exact proportion to your confidence. No
extreme positions. No corner solutions from estimation noise.
The practical result: BL portfolios look like real portfolios
— diversified, intuitive, tilted in the direction of your
convictions rather than dominated by optimization artifacts.
Common abuse one: setting tau incorrectly. Many practitioners default tau to
1, which makes the prior too uncertain and lets views dominate
— reintroducing the instability BL was designed to fix.
Common abuse two: treating omega as diagonal. This assumes view
errors are uncorrelated — fine if views are truly independent,
but wrong if they share a common macro driver.
Common abuse three: using only absolute views. Absolute views are harder to
calibrate and more sensitive to error. Prefer relative views — asset A
beats B by X percent — which are more natural and stable.
BL maps directly to DeFi yield optimization. The equilibrium
prior is the current yield allocation across protocols.
Your views are protocol-specific forecasts. For example: Aave's utilization
will increase by 15%, boosting supply APY by 2%.
Or: Curve's CRV incentives will be cut in the
next governance vote, reducing pool APY by 3%.
These views are expressed in the P matrix, and BL blends
them with the equilibrium yield allocation to produce stable reallocation weights
— without the extreme positions classical MVO would generate.
The key insight of BL: start from the market, not from guesses.
When you have no view, hold the market. When you have a
view, tilt proportionally to your confidence. When you have strong conviction, set
a small omega and let the view move the posterior.
The formula ensures your views are incorporated in a
mathematically coherent way that classical MVO simply cannot achieve.
Next: the Kelly Criterion — the mathematically optimal bet sizing
formula, why it's dangerous to use naively, and the fractional
Kelly compromise professionals use in practice. Subscribe. QuantiFire.